<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:cc="http://cyber.law.harvard.edu/rss/creativeCommonsRssModule.html">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Stories by Iram Ahmed on Medium]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Stories by Iram Ahmed on Medium]]></description>
        <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/fit/c/150/150/1*DI3GvJdKR-K84GooF05YcQ.jpeg</url>
            <title>Stories by Iram Ahmed on Medium</title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
        </image>
        <generator>Medium</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2026 08:16:22 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <webMaster><![CDATA[yourfriends@medium.com]]></webMaster>
        <atom:link href="http://medium.superfeedr.com" rel="hub"/>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Get Stronger as You Age: A Modern Guide to Building Muscle and Vitality]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/how-to-get-stronger-as-you-age-a-modern-guide-to-building-muscle-and-vitality-450ed2e86a60?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/450ed2e86a60</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[fitness]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[bodybuilding]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[health]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[life]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[muscle-building]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 19:40:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2026-01-03T19:40:31.655Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In an era where longevity is the new luxury, getting stronger as you age isn’t just about vanity — it’s a strategic investment in your future self. By 2026, with advancements in personalized fitness tech and nutrition science, defying the natural decline of muscle mass (known as sarcopenia) has never been more accessible. Sarcopenia kicks in around age 30, accelerating after 50, leading to a 3–5% loss of muscle every decade if unchecked.</p><p>But here’s the empowering truth: through targeted resistance training, smart nutrition, and cutting-edge tools, you can not only slow this process but reverse it, adding years of independent, vibrant living. This article dives deep into the science-backed strategies, drawing from recent research and real-world applications to help you thrive, not just survive, in your later years.</p><p>Why Strength Matters More Than Ever as You Age</p><p>Aging isn’t synonymous with weakness. In fact, building strength can transform how you experience life. Resistance training preserves muscle mass, boosts metabolism, and enhances bone density, reducing the risk of osteoporosis and fractures.</p><p>It also improves balance and coordination, slashing fall risks by up to 30% — a critical factor since falls are a leading cause of injury in older adults.</p><p>Beyond the physical, strength training sharpens cognitive function, combats depression, and even supports better sleep.</p><p>Studies like the Baltimore Longitudinal Study of Aging show that muscle peaks in your 30s and declines faster after 65 for women and 70 for men, but regular strength work can halt this slide.</p><p>For those with obesity, combining strength training with aerobic exercise reverses frailty and builds muscle while shedding fat. The result? More “healthy years” — time spent active and independent, not sidelined by limitations.</p><p>In today’s world, strength also ties into metabolic health. As muscle mass dips, so does your ability to process sugars and fats, heightening risks for diabetes and heart disease. But resistance exercises trigger DNA changes in muscles that linger for hours, optimizing energy use. Think of it as biohacking your body for longevity.</p><p>Debunking Common Myths About Aging and Strength</p><p>Myth 1: “It’s too late to start.” False — benefits accrue at any age. Even octogenarians in studies gained muscle and strength with consistent training.</p><p>Myth 2: “Lifting weights is dangerous for older joints.” With proper form and progression, it’s protective, cushioning joints and reducing arthritis symptoms.</p><p>Myth 3: “Cardio is enough.” Aerobics are great, but without resistance, you lose muscle. Aim for a blend: 150 minutes of moderate cardio weekly plus strength sessions.</p><p>Myth 4: “Women bulk up too much.” Strength training builds lean muscle without excessive bulk, especially with age-related hormonal shifts.</p><p>Getting Started: Safety First in Your Strength Journey</p><p>Before diving in, consult your doctor, especially if you’re over 40, inactive, or have conditions like heart disease or joint issues. Use tools like the PAR-Q questionnaire to assess readiness. Start slow: Warm up with 5–10 minutes of walking, and begin with bodyweight exercises before adding resistance.</p><p>Frequency matters — aim for 2–3 non-consecutive days per week, allowing recovery. Each session: 20–30 minutes, focusing on major muscle groups with 1–2 sets of 8–15 reps. Choose resistance that fatigues you by the last reps but maintains form. Progress gradually: Increase weight when reps feel easy.</p><p>Incorporate balance and flexibility: Add yoga or tai chi for 2 hours weekly to enhance coordination. Make it enjoyable — group classes boost motivation and accountability.</p><p>Core Strategies: Resistance Training Tailored for Aging</p><p>Resistance training is king for muscle building. Use free weights, bands, machines, or bodyweight. For beginners, programs like the CDC’s “Growing Stronger” offer a phased approach: Weeks 1–2 bodyweight, then add dumbbells (2–5 lbs) and ankle weights.</p><p>Key types:</p><ul><li>Bodyweight: Squats, push-ups, planks — accessible anywhere.</li><li>Free Weights: Dumbbells for curls, presses — build functional strength.</li><li>Machines: Safer for beginners, isolating muscles.</li><li>Bands: Portable, joint-friendly resistance.</li><li>Innovative: Weighted vests for daily wear to load bones during weight loss.</li></ul><p>Combine with aerobics and balance for holistic gains. Track with a journal or app to monitor progress.</p><p>10 Essential Exercises to Build Strength and Age Gracefully</p><p>From recent expert recommendations, here are 10 compound moves that target multiple muscles, boosting efficiency. Perform 2–3 sets of 8–12 reps, 2–3x/week.</p><p>Squats: Stand feet shoulder-width, lower as if sitting, stand up. Builds legs, core; improves daily mobility.</p><p>Deadlifts: Hinge at hips to lift weight from floor. Strengthens back, glutes; prevents injuries.</p><p>Push-Ups: From plank, lower and push up. Targets upper body; aids in fall prevention.</p><p>Walking Lunges: Step forward, lower, alternate. Enhances balance, legs; supports metabolic health.</p><p>Planks: Hold forearm plank. Core stabilizer; reduces inflammation, preserves posture.</p><p>Single-Arm Rows: Pull weight to side while supported. Balances upper back; improves heart health.</p><p>Seated Shoulder Press: Press weights overhead from seated. Builds shoulders; maintains overhead reach.</p><p>Glute Bridges: Lift hips from lying position. Targets glutes; eases back pain, boosts bone density.</p><p>Step-Ups: Step onto a platform, alternate. Improves coordination; prevents frailty.</p><p>Kettlebell Carries: Walk holding weights. Grip and core builder; linked to longevity.</p><p>Add CDC-inspired moves like toe stands for calves or pelvic tilts for core.</p><p>Fueling Your Gains: Nutrition for Muscle Building in Later Life</p><p>Exercise alone isn’t enough — nutrition amplifies results. Older adults need more protein to combat anabolic resistance: Aim for 1.0–1.6g per kg body weight daily (e.g., 80–120g for a 150lb person). Spread it across meals, focusing on leucine-rich sources like eggs, fish, dairy, and lean meats.</p><p>Key foods:</p><p>Protein Powerhouses: Chicken, salmon, Greek yogurt, beans — aim for 25–30g per meal.</p><p>Vitamin D Boosters: Fatty fish, fortified milk; supplements if deficient, as it aids muscle function.</p><p>Other Essentials: Vitamin B12 from fortified foods or supplements for energy; omega-3s from nuts/fish for inflammation control.</p><p>Supplements: Whey protein shakes post-workout, combined with amino acids and vitamin D, show significant muscle gains in studies. For sarcopenia, a moderately high-protein diet (1.2g/kg) preserves mass. Follow a Mediterranean-style diet for overall anti-aging benefits.</p><p>Calorie balance: If losing weight, pair with exercise to avoid muscle loss.</p><p>Recovery: The Unsung Hero of Strength Gains</p><p>Aging demands smarter recovery. Prioritize 7–9 hours of sleep nightly — it’s when muscles repair. Include rest days, gentle stretching (20–30 seconds per muscle post-workout), and mindfulness like tai chi. Hydrate well and manage stress to optimize hormone levels.</p><p>Listen to your body: If sore, scale back. Address issues like joint pain with physical therapy.</p><p>Modern Tools: Apps, Wearables, and Tech for 2026 Strength Building</p><p>Embrace tech for personalized progress. AI-powered apps like Fitbod generate custom workouts based on your age, goals, and feedback, adapting for muscle building. Caliber offers science-based coaching for measurable gains. For tracking, apps like StrongLifts 5x5 log lifts simply.</p><p>Wearables: The Apple Watch or advanced trackers sync with apps for heart rate, form analysis, and recovery metrics. Body composition scales provide instant muscle/fat feedback.</p><p>Supplements go high-tech: Apps like Oneleaf integrate tracking with personalized vitamin D/whey recommendations.</p><p>Tracking Progress and Staying Motivated</p><p>Measure beyond the scale: Track reps, weights, or functional tests like the Short Physical Performance Battery (standing from a chair, balance, walk speed). Set goals like “carry groceries easier” for real-life wins. Join communities via apps or classes for support.</p><p>If plateaus hit, vary routines or up protein.</p><p>Conclusion: Strength as Your Superpower</p><p>Getting stronger as you age is a proactive choice, blending timeless exercises with 2026’s innovations. By committing to resistance training, nutrient-dense eating, and tech-assisted tracking, you’ll not only build muscle but reclaim vitality. Remember, any movement counts — start today, and watch your future self thank you. For personalized advice, consult professionals, but know this: Your strongest years could still be ahead.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=450ed2e86a60" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mumbai New Year Party Horror Story]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/mumbai-new-year-party-horror-story-ea98d3ca0b15?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/ea98d3ca0b15</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[india]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[paranormal]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[short-story]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[mumbai]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[horror]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 14:19:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2026-01-03T14:19:04.989Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jasan, <strong>Ranay</strong>, and <strong>Aniket</strong> were three inseparable friends living in <strong>Nagpur</strong>. They had been friends since childhood and shared the same dream — to go to Mumbai and join the film industry. But they had no clear idea of <em>how</em> to enter it. They continued with their studies, and by the time they reached <strong>10th grade</strong>, they became clear about one thing: they loved <strong>costume design</strong> and wanted to enter the film industry through that path.</p><p>They began researching even while in 10th grade. By the time they reached <strong>11th</strong>, they realized they could pursue a <strong>fashion designing course</strong>. If they did it from Mumbai, it would make entry into the film industry much easier.</p><p>They spoke to their families — and their families supported them wholeheartedly. Their parents said,<br> “If you go directly to Mumbai for a fashion designing course, it’ll take time to understand the city. You’ve just entered 11th grade — why not transfer now and move there properly?”</p><p>All three families knew each other well. The boys had studied in the same school since childhood. After mutual discussion, their parents arranged admissions for all three in Mumbai.</p><p>They began living in <strong>Malad</strong>, Mumbai, and completed <strong>11th and 12th</strong> from a nearby junior college, doing very well academically.</p><p>Now, 12th grade was complete. December arrived. The boys were extremely excited — they had finally turned <strong>18</strong>. Until now, they had never been to clubs or pubs. Everything they’d seen was only on TV. They were desperate to go.</p><p>They eagerly waited for <strong>December 31st</strong>, because now they were legally allowed to enter clubs. Their IDs were valid, and finally, New Year’s Eve arrived.</p><p>They canceled all other plans with classmates. That same year — <em>the year they turned 18</em> — they had also secured admission into a good fashion designing college. Their biggest dream was coming true… yet that night, in the name of a party, something horrific was about to happen.</p><p>On the night of the 31st, they searched for clubs in Malad. Most clubs charged an entry fee, but one club — a shady-looking one — had <strong>no entry fee</strong>.</p><p>Money wasn’t an issue; they came from well-off families. But they didn’t understand concepts like stag entry or cover charges. So they decided to go to this “normal” club, even if it looked shady.</p><p>After all, they were 18 now. They wanted to <em>feel</em> it.</p><p>The club was slightly inside the Malad area, in a not-so-good location. Still, it was packed with people. Two or three bouncers stood at the entrance. Finally, they entered the club around <strong>11:00 PM</strong>.</p><p>They knew that once the clock struck <strong>12</strong>, there would be chaos — New Year celebrations, eating, drinking, dancing. They started drinking heavily. By the time it was nearing midnight, all three were completely drunk.</p><p>Dim lights filled the club — the kind you see in cheap places. Music was loud, people were dancing, food and drinks were flowing.</p><p>About <strong>15 minutes before midnight</strong>, Ranay and Aniket told Jasan,<br> “Bro, we really need to use the washroom.”</p><p>Both of them went together.</p><p>Jasan stayed at the table with a beer glass and a plate of spicy snacks — roasted chickpeas mixed with green chilies and fried garlic. He kept eating chilies and sipping beer.</p><p>Suddenly, the spice hit him hard. He began having violent hiccups. His friends were in the washroom, and he sat there alone, hiccupping uncontrollably.</p><p>At that moment, a <strong>girl approached him</strong>.</p><p>Who was she? Let me explain.</p><p>Since the moment they entered the club, Jasan’s eyes had been fixed on one girl. She stood out from everyone else. She wore a <strong>glittering red saree</strong>, shining brilliantly under the club lights. The reflection made her glow differently from anyone else. Her beauty was indescribable — according to Jasan, even big celebrities would pale before her.</p><p>They kept exchanging glances. She seemed to notice him too, but she was with her friend group, so she didn’t approach.</p><p>Now that Jasan was alone and hiccupping, she came to his table and asked,<br> “Are you okay? Drink some water — it must be too spicy.”</p><p>She ran and brought him a glass of water. His hiccups stopped, but the burning didn’t. Tears streamed from his eyes.</p><p>Then she said,<br> “If the spiciness hasn’t gone, I have candy. Eat one — it’ll help.”</p><p>Feeling awkward yet mesmerized, Jasan agreed. She took out a candy from her small purse. As soon as he ate it, he felt immediate relief.</p><p>“That was amazing,” he said. “What candy is this?”</p><p>She smiled and said,<br> “Forget it. I have many like these. I’m going outside to smoke. Do you smoke?”</p><p>He didn’t — but said yes anyway.</p><p>Smoking wasn’t allowed inside, so she led him outside. Then she said she couldn’t smoke openly on the road and suggested a <strong>back alley</strong>.</p><p>Drunk, excited, and completely trusting her, Jasan followed.</p><p>Behind the club was a <strong>narrow, deserted alley</strong>. No people. No dogs. Just darkness. Loud music played inside the club, but outside, everything was silent.</p><p>She walked ahead. He followed.</p><p>She stopped at the <strong>very end of the alley</strong>, where there was no exit — only a wall.</p><p>Jasan said nervously,<br> “We’ve come too far in. Someone might see us.”</p><p>She didn’t respond. She stood facing the wall.</p><p>Feeling uneasy, Jasan moved closer to see her face.</p><p>And the moment he did —</p><p>The ground slipped from beneath his feet.</p><p>Her face was <strong>not human</strong>. It looked as if it were <strong>melting</strong>, like wax dripping. She had <strong>no pupils</strong>. Her mouth was wide open, releasing black smoke.</p><p>He screamed violently and collapsed.</p><p>The bouncers heard his screams and rushed to the alley — but found <strong>no girl</strong>.</p><p>They assumed Jasan was extremely drunk and dragged him back to the club entrance, gave him water, but he kept trembling uncontrollably.</p><p>His phone rang. The bouncer answered — it was Ranay shouting from inside the club.</p><p>They were called outside. Seeing Jasan’s condition, the bouncers threw them out and told them to go home.</p><p>On the way home in an auto, Jasan told them everything. They dismissed it as hallucination — none of them had seen such a girl.</p><p>Suddenly, the auto took a <strong>shortcut through a dark forest-like road</strong>. The auto stopped. The driver stepped out — and vanished.</p><p>Terrified, the three ran for their lives.</p><p>As they ran, Aniket and Ranay realized <strong>Jasan wasn’t running</strong>.</p><p>They turned back.</p><p>Jasan stood frozen. When Aniket touched him, Jasan lifted his eyes — <strong>no pupils</strong> — and let out a piercing scream.</p><p>Birds flew away. Dogs howled. The forest erupted.</p><p>Ranay and Aniket ran, leaving Jasan behind.</p><p>They reached home, locked the door — and then heard knocking.</p><p>Jasan stood outside — soaked, expressionless, foul-smelling.</p><p>He went inside, took off his clothes, locked himself in the bathroom, and kept the shower running for <strong>hours</strong>.</p><p>He never came out.</p><p>His parents were called. When they arrived, they found Jasan naked, scribbling nonsense all over the walls with a pen, water flooding everywhere.</p><p>He was taken back to Nagpur for treatment.</p><p><strong>Ten years have passed. It’s now 2025.</strong></p><p>Jasan has never fully recovered.</p><p>He sits silently. Eats when told. Sleeps when told.</p><p>Doctors say his mind is destroyed. No scientific reason.</p><p>Only one explanation remains —</p><p><strong>The Paranormal World.</strong></p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=ea98d3ca0b15" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unearthing Ghosts in the Sand: The 7,000-Year-Old Sahara Mummies That Rewrite Human History]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/unearthing-ghosts-in-the-sand-the-7-000-year-old-sahara-mummies-that-rewrite-human-history-3e8e328cc92c?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/3e8e328cc92c</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[human-history]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[africa]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[sahara]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[science]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[birth]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 17:51:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2026-01-02T17:51:45.197Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In a world obsessed with ancestry tests and DNA kits that promise to unlock your family’s hidden stories, imagine stumbling upon ancient remains whose genetic code doesn’t just surprise scientists — it outright baffles them. That’s exactly what happened in the scorching dunes of southwestern Libya, where two remarkably preserved mummies, dating back roughly 7,000 years, have revealed a lost chapter of humanity. These aren’t your typical Egyptian pharaohs wrapped in linen; they’re natural mummies, desiccated by the harsh desert environment, and their DNA points to a “ghost” lineage — a branch of our family tree that vanished without leaving heirs in the modern world. Dubbed a population “from nowhere on Earth” by sensational headlines, this discovery is shaking up our understanding of ancient migrations, cultural exchanges, and even how innovations like farming spread across continents. Let’s dive deep into the science, the surprises, and why this matters in 2026, when genetic tech is advancing faster than ever.</p><p>The Green Sahara: A Lush Paradise Lost</p><p>To grasp the significance of these mummies, we need to rewind the clock — not just to 5,000 BCE, but to the broader era known as the African Humid Period, or more poetically, the “Green Sahara.” Between about 14,000 and 5,000 years ago, what we now know as the world’s largest hot desert was a thriving savanna. Picture vast grasslands dotted with acacia trees, permanent lakes teeming with fish, and rivers snaking through the landscape. Mega-fauna like hippopotamuses, elephants, giraffes, and crocodiles roamed freely, alongside early human communities who hunted, gathered, and eventually domesticated animals.</p><p>This transformation was driven by shifts in Earth’s orbit and monsoon patterns, pulling rainy weather northward and turning the Sahara into a habitable zone. Archaeological evidence from sites across North Africa paints a picture of bustling human activity: rock art depicting cattle herding, pottery shards from communal feasts, and burial sites that hint at complex social structures. But by around 3,000 BCE, climate change dried it all up, forcing populations to migrate or adapt — leading to the barren expanse we see today.</p><p>It was in this once-verdant backdrop that the Takarkori rock shelter emerged as a time capsule. Nestled in the Tadrart Acacus mountains near the Algerian border, this site — accessible only by rugged four-wheel-drive vehicles — has been excavated since 2003 by teams from Italy’s Sapienza University of Rome and other institutions. Among the finds: 15 burials of women and children, complete with artifacts like baskets, tools, and animal bones. But the stars of the show are two adult women, around 40 years old at death, whose bodies were naturally mummified by the dry air and sand. Their skin, ligaments, and even some organs remained intact, a rare gift from nature’s freezer (or in this case, dehydrator).</p><p>These mummies weren’t royalty; they were everyday herders. Evidence suggests they lived as semi-nomadic pastoralists, tending to sheep, goats, and cattle while supplementing their diet with wild game and fish from nearby waterways. Rock paintings nearby show scenes of daily life, including herding and hunting, underscoring a society in transition from hunter-gatherer roots to early agriculture.</p><p>Cracking the Genetic Code: A Forensic Feat in the Lab</p><p>Extracting DNA from ancient remains is no small task, especially in a hot, arid region like the Sahara, where heat and dryness can fragment genetic material into useless snippets. Typically, ancient DNA (aDNA) thrives in cold, stable environments like permafrost or caves — think Ötzi the Iceman from the Alps. But the Takarkori mummies defied the odds, thanks to their natural preservation.</p><p>The breakthrough came from researchers at the Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology in Leipzig, Germany, a hub for cutting-edge genomics. In 2019, they first managed to sequence the mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) from these remains — the maternal lineage passed down through mothers. But that was just a teaser. By 2025, using advanced techniques, they reconstructed full nuclear genomes from the two women. This involved pulverizing tiny bone samples (often from the inner ear, where DNA hides best), extracting degraded fragments, and piecing them together like a billion-piece puzzle with computational algorithms.</p><p>The process required “fine-tuning methods to work with very tiny amounts of DNA,” as one researcher noted, battling contamination from modern microbes and handling the short, broken strands typical of aDNA.</p><p>Tools like next-generation sequencing and bioinformatics software allowed them to map the genomes against modern and ancient references, revealing not just who these people were related to, but how isolated their group had been.</p><p>The DNA Bombshell: A ‘Ghost’ Lineage Emerges</p><p>Here’s where things get mind-bending. The genomes showed that these 7,000-year-old women belonged to a previously unknown North African lineage — a genetic branch that diverged from the ancestors of modern sub-Saharan Africans around 50,000 years ago. That’s roughly the same time as the major “Out of Africa” migrations, when Homo sapiens began spreading across Eurasia, eventually mixing with Neanderthals and other archaic humans.</p><p>But unlike those wanderers, this Sahara group stayed put, genetically speaking. They remained isolated for tens of thousands of years, with minimal intermixing from neighboring populations. For context, that’s longer than the entire history of recorded civilization. Their DNA shows a moderately large population size with little inbreeding, suggesting a stable community that thrived in the Green Sahara without much outside influence.</p><p>One striking detail: these mummies carried far less Neanderthal DNA — about ten times less than non-African populations today. This underscores their African roots, as Neanderthal admixture happened mostly outside the continent. Yet, their lineage isn’t a perfect match for any modern group. Scientists call it a “ghost” branch because it left only faint echoes in contemporary genomes, detectable through advanced modeling but not as direct descendants. As lead researcher Ron Pinhasi put it in interviews, these people were “almost like living fossils,” with genomes that could fool you into thinking they were 40,000 years old.</p><p>Comparisons to other ancient DNA samples paint a clearer picture. Unlike European hunter-gatherers or Near Eastern farmers, who show waves of migration and mixing, the Takarkori people had no significant input from sub-Saharan groups to the south or Mediterranean populations to the north. This challenges the long-held idea that the Green Sahara acted as a bustling highway for human movement, linking Africa’s diverse regions. Instead, it seems more like a genetic cul-de-sac — a pocket of isolation amid a changing world.</p><p>Cultural Exchanges Without Genetic Mix: How Pastoralism Spread</p><p>The plot thickens when we look at their lifestyle. These people were pastoralists, herding livestock — a practice that originated in the Near East around 10,000 years ago and spread across Africa. But how did it reach the isolated Sahara folk without genetic traces of migrants?</p><p>The answer lies in cultural diffusion: ideas and technologies traveling through trade, alliances, or casual encounters, rather than mass population movements. Artifacts at Takarkori include pottery styles from the Nile Valley, sub-Saharan Africa, and beyond, hinting at extensive networks. Sheep and goats, domesticated elsewhere, appeared in the region without the herders’ DNA showing up in the locals. As study co-author Savino di Lernia explained, “Despite genetic isolation, the Takarkori people engaged in cultural exchanges,” evidenced by shared tools and art.</p><p>This flips older theories on their head. Archaeologists once assumed pastoralism arrived via waves of farmers from the Levant or Egypt, replacing or intermarrying with locals. But the DNA says otherwise: knowledge hopped borders, while genes stayed home. It’s a reminder that human history isn’t just about conquest and migration — it’s also about memes (in the original sense: ideas that replicate).</p><p>Broader Implications: Rewriting Africa’s Untold Story</p><p>This discovery isn’t just a cool ancient trivia point; it has ripple effects for how we view human evolution in 2026. Africa, often called the cradle of humanity, has a notoriously understudied genetic history due to poor preservation and fewer research sites compared to Europe. Findings like this highlight the continent’s diversity, revealing “lost” lineages that could reshape models of Out of Africa events.</p><p>For instance, it questions whether the Sahara was ever a true bridge between north and south. During the Green Period, it could have supported up to a million people, yet gene flow was minimal. This isolation might explain why some modern North Africans have unique genetic markers — faint remnants of these ghosts.</p><p>On a modern note, think about climate change. The Green Sahara’s collapse mirrors today’s environmental shifts: rising temperatures, desertification, and forced migrations. Understanding how ancient populations adapted (or didn’t) could inform strategies for vulnerable regions like the Sahel.</p><p>Ethically, the research emphasizes respectful handling of remains. The mummies were studied with input from Libyan authorities, and the data is open for global scientists, fostering collaboration in a politically turbulent area.</p><p>The Future: More Ghosts to Hunt?</p><p>As genomic tech evolves — think CRISPR-level precision and AI-driven analysis — we’re bound to uncover more surprises. The Takarkori study, published in Nature in 2025, calls for sequencing more Green Sahara sites to map the full population mosaic. Who knows? There might be other ghost branches lurking in the sand, waiting to stun us again.</p><p>In an era where DNA apps like 23andMe make ancestry feel personal, these mummies remind us that our story is vaster and weirder than we thought. They’re not from “nowhere on Earth” — they’re from a forgotten somewhere, a lush oasis that time erased. And in decoding their secrets, we’re piecing together the puzzle of us all.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=3e8e328cc92c" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2025: A Rollercoaster of Triumphs, Turmoil, and Total Chaos]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/2025-a-rollercoaster-of-triumphs-turmoil-and-total-chaos-6537d301edb7?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/6537d301edb7</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[economy]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[year-in-review]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[politics]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[weather]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[happy-new-year]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 08:31:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2026-01-01T08:31:47.659Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As the clock strikes midnight on January 1, 2026, we’re finally bidding adieu to 2025 — a year that felt like a binge-watch of a dystopian sci-fi series mixed with viral TikTok trends and unexpected plot twists. From AI breakthroughs that redefined innovation to geopolitical shake-ups that redrew global alliances, 2025 was anything but boring. But let’s be real: it was a mixed bag. Economies boomed in some corners while crumbling in others; tech soared while the planet simmered; and politics? Well, it was pure theater, complete with comebacks, coups, and ceaseless drama.</p><p>In this deep-dive review, we’ll break it down into the good (the wins that gave us hope), the bad (the setbacks that tested our resilience), and the downright ugly (the moments that made us question humanity). Drawing from a whirlwind of headlines, social media buzz, and expert analyses, here’s the unfiltered recap of a year that kept the world scrolling, debating, and occasionally facepalming.</p><p>The Good: Breakthroughs, Booms, and Bright Spots</p><p>2025 wasn’t all doomscrolling — there were genuine highs that sparked optimism. Economies stabilized in unexpected ways, tech leaped forward, and some global hotspots cooled off. Here’s the uplift we needed.</p><p>Economic Wins and Surprising Surpluses</p><p>Despite predictions of recession, the global economy showed grit. In the U.S., Donald Trump’s return to the White House kicked off with tariffs that, against all odds, generated $90 billion in revenue, contributing to a $27 billion federal surplus — the first since the MySpace era.</p><p>Unemployment held steady at around 4.2%, with 671,000 new jobs going entirely to Americans. Consumer spending surged, especially among high- and middle-income groups, fueled by tax cuts that put an extra $13,300 in family pockets annually. Inflation hovered at 3%, but prices for essentials like eggs and gas plummeted, making everyday life a bit less wallet-draining.</p><p>Globally, emerging markets shone. Argentina, under Javier Milei, notched its first budget surplus since 2008, while El Salvador’s Nayib Bukele slashed crime by 95% through aggressive reforms. India’s economy powered ahead, with markets buoyed by steady SIP investments and a flurry of IPOs. China, defying U.S. sabotage attempts, solidified its lead in EVs, batteries, solar, and AI, boosting trade surpluses with partners and settling deals in local currencies. Even silver prices skyrocketed 160%, driven by industrial demand and Asian buyers, signaling a shift in global commodity pricing.</p><p>Economic Highlights of 2025</p><p>U.S. Tariff Revenue</p><p>Key Stats</p><p>$90B</p><p>Impact</p><p>Funded surplus, reduced deficits</p><p>Economic Highlights of 2025</p><p>U.S. Job Growth</p><p>Key Stats</p><p>671K (all to Americans)</p><p>Impact</p><p>Boosted consumer confidence</p><p>Economic Highlights of 2025</p><p>Argentina Surplus</p><p>Key Stats</p><p>First since 2008</p><p>Impact</p><p>Stabilized economy amid reforms</p><p>Economic Highlights of 2025</p><p>China Trade Shift</p><p>Key Stats</p><p>Increased local currency settlements</p><p>Impact</p><p>Reduced USD dominance</p><p>Economic Highlights of 2025</p><p>Silver Price Surge</p><p>Key Stats</p><p>160%</p><p>Impact</p><p>Benefited miners and investors</p><p>Tech and Innovation Leaps</p><p>If 2025 had a theme song, it’d be something from a futuristic soundtrack. AI agents became autonomous workhorses, planning and executing tasks without constant human input. Google’s breakthroughs spanned AI models, robotics, and scientific advancements, accelerating progress in health care and beyond. The World Economic Forum’s top emerging tech list included structural battery composites (for lighter EVs), osmotic power systems (harnessing saltwater energy), advanced nuclear tech, engineered living therapeutics, and next-gen GLP-1 drugs for health. NVIDIA’s market cap eclipsed India’s GDP, underscoring AI’s dominance.</p><p>In biotech and materials, innovations like cryptography, lasers, neuroscience, and semiconductors pushed boundaries. Apple’s $500B AI investment and U.S. Steel’s revival highlighted reshoring efforts, though challenges loomed. On X, users hailed these as “the year tech went god-mode.”</p><p>Peace Deals and Social Progress</p><p>Diplomatically, Trump brokered ceasefires in Gaza, Ukraine, and parts of Africa, freeing hostages and dialing back tensions. Iran curbed its nuclear ambitions, and NATO allies ponied up more funding. Border crossings dropped 96%, with cartels labeled terrorists and deportations ramping up. Violent crime hit record lows, obesity trended down, and life expectancy ticked up. In sports, India swept men’s and women’s Cricket World Cups, while tennis bid farewell to the “Big 3.”</p><p>Entertainment delivered feel-goods: Beyoncé’s Cowboy Carter made history as the first Black woman to win a Grammy for Best Country Album. Hits like Chaava, The Family Man, and Delhi Crime revived storytelling. Taylor Swift’s engagement and Robert Irwin’s win went viral.</p><p>The Bad: Setbacks, Struggles, and Systemic Fails</p><p>Not everything glittered. 2025 exposed cracks in systems we thought were solid, from economic inequalities to environmental tipping points.</p><p>Economic and Financial Woes</p><p>While some economies thrived, others faltered. U.S. credit card debt and auto loan defaults hit 15-year highs, with 1.2 million layoffs — the most since 2009. Large company bankruptcies spiked, farmers needed bailouts, and consumer confidence plummeted to all-time lows. Global growth slowed to 3.2%, with advanced economies dragging. Trump’s tariffs backfired initially, sparking retaliations and frictions. In Europe, de-industrialization and welfare dismantling accelerated under military spending pressures.</p><p>Reshoring dreams fizzled: The U.S. lacked grids, infrastructure, and skilled workers for manufacturing booms, stalling AI data centers. Japan grappled with exploding rates, while China’s crisis kept rates near zero.</p><p>Environmental and Climate Crises</p><p>The planet didn’t get a break. Global warming from fossil fuels topped the list of issues, with fossil fuel dependence, food waste, biodiversity loss, and plastic pollution close behind. Extreme weather — heatwaves, floods, air pollution — disproportionately hit vulnerable groups. Melting glaciers released ancient microbes and toxins, while green tech’s lithium demand sparked new crises. Europe backtracked on emissions and deforestation rules, underscoring policy failures.</p><p>Top Environmental Issues</p><p>Global Warming</p><p>Severity</p><p>High</p><p>Examples</p><p>Fossil fuels driving heatwaves</p><p>Top Environmental Issues</p><p>Biodiversity Loss</p><p>Severity</p><p>Critical</p><p>Examples</p><p>Deforestation accelerating</p><p>Top Environmental Issues</p><p>Plastic Pollution</p><p>Severity</p><p>Widespread</p><p>Examples</p><p>Oceans choked with waste</p><p>Top Environmental Issues</p><p>Air Pollution</p><p>Severity</p><p>Urgent</p><p>Examples</p><p>Floods unleashing toxins</p><p>Political and Social Turbulence</p><p>Trump’s term started with anti-woke measures but devolved into arbitrariness, fracturing the MAGA coalition. The longest U.S. government shutdown in history ensued. Globally, coups in Africa, Gen Z protests in Nepal, and right-wing wins in Latin America heightened instability. Wars in Ukraine, Gaza, and Sudan dragged on, with negotiations stalling. The EU’s repressive apparatus expanded, using debanking against dissenters.</p><p>Health agencies faced turmoil under Trump and RFK Jr., with Covid policy disinformation exposed. Bigotry, inequality, and unmitigated virus spread remained grim reminders.</p><p>The Downright Ugly: Scandals, Tragedies, and Moral Lows</p><p>This is where 2025 got dark — genocides, disasters, and depravity that scarred the collective psyche.</p><p>Wars, Genocides, and Atrocities</p><p>A live-streamed genocide in Gaza, backed by Western powers, eroded global credibility. Russia’s Ukraine invasion entered year four, with U.S. strikes adding fuel. Sudan’s civil war grinded on, while India-Pakistan clashes escalated. Russian hybrid attacks and a new American pope’s election defined chaos.</p><p>Disasters and Attacks</p><p>Terrorist strikes hit hard: New Orleans attack, California wildfires, a mid-air collision, and a Cybertruck explosion at Trump Tower. In India, bridge collapses, bus fires, and stampedes killed dozens. Epstein files dropped bombshells, alongside assassinations (Charlie Kirk) and celebrity deaths.</p><p>Corruption and Repression</p><p>Trump’s Epstein debacle and Iran strike were major fumbles. Authoritarianism surged: Troops in U.S. cities, pardons for cronies, and Qatari bribes. In the UK, Keir Starmer’s rape cover-up exploded. Censorship-industrial complex revelations and EU sanctions without trials chilled free speech.</p><p>Pop culture had its lows too: Katy Perry’s space trip (weird), Dharam paaji’s passing, and forgotten viral fails.</p><p>Wrapping Up 2025: Lessons from the Madness</p><p>2025 was a testament to human ingenuity and folly — AI soared while wars raged, economies rebounded amid inequalities, and the planet begged for mercy. As X user</p><p>@MarioNawfal</p><p>put it, “Love him or hate him, 2025 is Trump’s year,” but it was also ours: a year of awakening nationalisms, tech revolutions, and harsh realities.</p><p>Heading into 2026, let’s carry the goods (innovation, peace efforts) and ditch the uglies (division, destruction). Here’s to a smoother ride ahead — fingers crossed.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=6537d301edb7" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Picchi Hannan: The Street Kid Who Became Dhaka’s Most Feared Underworld Kingpin]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/picchi-hannan-the-street-kid-who-became-dhakas-most-feared-underworld-kingpin-70860e9e0536?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/70860e9e0536</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[crime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[dhaka]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[true-crime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[bangladesh]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[law]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 17:51:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2025-12-31T17:51:05.594Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the chaotic underbelly of Dhaka, where poverty clashes with power and survival demands ruthless ambition, few names evoke as much terror and intrigue as Picchi Hannan. Born into humble beginnings in rural Bangladesh, Hannan clawed his way from the streets to the pinnacle of organized crime, building an empire fueled by drugs, extortion, and murder. His story isn’t just a tale of rags to riches — it’s a gritty narrative of how politics, poverty, and violence intertwined in post-independence Bangladesh, turning a street kid into a gangster whose shadow loomed over the capital for over a decade. But like many before him, Hannan’s reign ended in a hail of bullets, courtesy of the state’s iron-fisted response to crime. This modern retelling dives deep into his life, drawing from historical accounts, police records, and the echoes of Dhaka’s underworld. Buckle up — it’s a wild ride through the dark side of the city.</p><p>The Humble Origins: From Rural Farmlands to Urban Survival</p><p>Picchi Hannan, whose real name was Hannan (the moniker “Picchi” meaning “kid” or “youngster” in Bengali slang, a nod to his early street days), was born in the quiet Faridganj Upazila of Chandpur District, southeast of Dhaka. Details about his exact birth year are murky — estimates place it in the late 1960s or early 1970s — but his childhood was marked by the grinding poverty that plagued much of rural Bangladesh in the aftermath of the 1971 Liberation War. His family wasn’t destitute by village standards; his father ran a modest business, but economic pressures pushed them toward the bustling capital.</p><p>As a teenager, Hannan relocated to Dhaka to help with his father’s operations in the sprawling Karwan Bazar, one of the city’s largest wholesale markets. Karwan Bazar was a melting pot of opportunity and desperation: vendors hawking fruits and spices, laborers hauling crates, and a constant undercurrent of illicit dealings. For a young Hannan, it was a crash course in urban survival. He started small — odd jobs, running errands — but the streets of Dhaka in the 1980s were unforgiving. Unemployment was rampant, and the post-war economy left many youths adrift. Hannan, like countless others, found himself drawn into the fringes of society.</p><p>Historians and criminologists often point to this era as the breeding ground for Bangladesh’s “mastan” culture — local slang for gangsters or enforcers who operated as violent intermediaries between the poor and the powerful. Hannan began his descent into crime with petty offenses: pickpocketing, small-time thefts, and street brawls. These weren’t glamorous; they were necessities in a city where the line between victim and perpetrator blurred. By his late teens, he had graduated to more organized hustles, forming loose alliances with other street kids. What set Hannan apart was his charisma and ruthlessness — he wasn’t just surviving; he was building a network.</p><p>Influences from this period are hard to pinpoint, but the socio-political chaos of the time played a role. Bangladesh was under military rule until 1990, with Ershad’s regime fostering corruption and patronage networks. Street kids like Hannan learned quickly that power came from muscle, not merit. He honed his skills in the shadows of Karwan Bazar, where business disputes often escalated into violence. It was here that he earned the nickname “Picchi,” a diminutive that belied his growing ferocity.</p><p>The Rise: Building an Empire of Fear and Loyalty</p><p>By the early 1990s, Hannan had transformed from a street urchin into a budding crime lord. His ascent coincided with Dhaka’s rapid urbanization — slums mushroomed, and the drug trade exploded, particularly phensedyl (a codeine-based cough syrup smuggled from India) and heroin. Hannan dove headfirst into narcotics, recognizing it as the quickest path to wealth and influence. He started by controlling distribution in areas like Agargaon, a working-class neighborhood ripe for exploitation.</p><p>A pivotal moment came when Hannan recruited Iqbal Hossain Nitel, a fresh graduate from BAF Shaheen College in Dhaka. Nitel wasn’t your typical thug; he had education and organizational skills, making him the perfect lieutenant. Hannan appointed him to oversee the narcotics operations in Agargaon, turning what was once a small-time racket into a structured enterprise. Under Hannan’s leadership, the gang expanded into robbery, extortion, and contract killings. They targeted businessmen, rival dealers, and anyone who crossed their path.</p><p>Hannan’s modus operandi was brutal efficiency. He built loyalty through a mix of fear and patronage — paying off underlings handsomely while eliminating threats without hesitation. By the mid-1990s, he was part of the infamous “Five-Star Group,” a loose coalition of top gangsters including Kala Jahangir, Dakat Shahid, and Zeesan Ahmed. This alliance dominated Dhaka’s south and old quarters, carving up territories like a mafia syndicate. The group was responsible for high-profile murders, such as the 2000 killing of Humayun Kabir Milon (aka Murgi Milon) right in the Old Dhaka Court premises — a brazen act that shocked the nation.</p><p>Rivals were plentiful in this cutthroat world. Kala Jahangir, often described as the “most feared gangster” of his time, was more of an associate than a foe, but turf wars were inevitable. Hannan clashed with figures like Mohammad Abu Hanif, a local political leader and businessman who aided police in Hannan’s 1998 arrest. After serving eight months in jail, Hannan emerged vengeful, placing a bounty on Hanif’s head. Hanif was gunned down in May 2006, long after Hannan’s death, suggesting his influence lingered.</p><p>Hannan’s criminal portfolio was diverse: drug trafficking, arms smuggling, land grabbing, and political muscle. He was accused in the 2001 Malibagh killings, where four people died during a political clash, implicating him alongside former Awami League MP HBM Iqbal. Another notch on his belt was the murder of Dhaka Ward Commissioner Shahadat Hossain Sikder, a hit that underscored his reach into municipal politics. In 2003, his followers even tortured juvenile delinquents at the Tongi Juvenile Development Centre, a chilling display of unchecked power.</p><p>What made Hannan untouchable for so long? Political connections. In Bangladesh’s polarized landscape, gangsters like him served as enforcers for parties. Reports suggest he was used by figures in the Bangladesh Nationalist Party (BNP), including then-Home Affairs Minister Lutfozzaman Babar, for dirty work like voter intimidation and silencing opponents. Hannan himself hinted at this during his final days, telling media that “politically connected groups had used him.”</p><p>The Height of Power: A Reign of Terror in Dhaka</p><p>At his peak in the early 2000s, Hannan was a mythical figure — whispers of his name sent shivers through Dhaka’s streets. His gang operated like a well-oiled machine: Nitel handled drugs, while others managed extortion rackets in markets and construction sites. Hannan’s wealth allowed him to live lavishly, with safe houses across the city and a network of informants in the police.</p><p>But power bred enemies. The Five-Star Group’s violence escalated, with hits on ward commissioners like Saidur Rahman Newton in 2002 and threats against political heavyweights. Hannan’s associates, like Nazimuddin Babu (a Chhatra League leader) and Shaheb Ali, extended his influence into student politics and beyond. In December 2004, one follower was shot dead in a skirmish, a sign that cracks were forming.</p><p>Public outcry grew. Dhaka’s residents, tired of gang wars spilling into daily life, demanded action. The government, under BNP-Jamaat alliance, responded with Operation Clean Heart in 2002–2003, a military-led anti-crime drive that set the stage for the Rapid Action Battalion (RAB) — an elite force blending police, army, and intelligence, notorious for extrajudicial killings.</p><p>The Downfall: From Capture to Crossfire</p><p>Hannan’s empire crumbled in the summer of 2004. On June 26, RAB and police raided a house in Uttara Model Town, sparking a fierce gunfight. Hannan and his men fired back, wounding two officers. Associates like Babul Mian and Rafiqul Islam Tuku were nabbed, while Nitel’s body was found nearby, wrapped in polythene — likely killed in the chaos.</p><p>The next day, June 27, RAB, led by Lt. Col. Chowdhury Fazlul Bari, stormed Al-Insaf Clinic in Savar, where Hannan was treating bullet wounds. Captured alongside associate Debashish Kumar Das (who later died in hospital), Hannan was remanded for 10 days. In a rare moment of candor, he accused politicians of exploiting him. He even offered a Tk 50 lakh bribe to RAB officials — a desperate bid for freedom that was rebuffed.</p><p>On August 6, 2004 — the seventh day of his remand — RAB took Hannan out for a “search operation.” What followed was a classic “crossfire” scenario: an alleged gunfight where Hannan was killed. His daughter later claimed it was execution for defying a BNP MP. An autopsy confirmed a single bullet to the head, fueling suspicions of foul play.</p><p>Hannan’s death marked a turning point. By November 2004, RAB had eliminated over 49 gangsters, instilling fear that made imprisonment preferable to resistance. His associates scattered: Babu detained in 2007, Ali killed in 2008.</p><p>Legacy: From Gangster to Cultural Icon</p><p>Two decades later, Picchi Hannan’s story endures as a cautionary tale of crime and corruption. He symbolized the dark nexus between poverty, politics, and violence in Bangladesh — a system where street kids become pawns in power games. His death highlighted RAB’s controversial tactics, with human rights groups decrying extrajudicial killings.</p><p>Culturally, Hannan has transcended infamy. In 2024, Dhallywood announced a biopic starring Joy Chowdhury, promising to unpack his complex life. True crime documentaries, like a 2025 YouTube feature, romanticize his journey from street kid to kingpin, blending fact with folklore.</p><p>Yet, his legacy is bittersweet. For Dhaka’s underclass, Hannan represented upward mobility through any means. For others, he’s a reminder of unchecked power’s cost. In a city still grappling with crime, his ghost lingers — proof that from the streets, legends are born, but rarely do they die peacefully.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=70860e9e0536" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Galkata Kamal: The Scarred Shadow of Dhaka’s Underworld]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/galkata-kamal-the-scarred-shadow-of-dhakas-underworld-1f26a38bc3b9?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/1f26a38bc3b9</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[dhaka]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[underworld]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[bangladesh]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[law]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[true-crime]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 18:04:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2025-12-30T18:04:15.435Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the labyrinthine streets of Old Dhaka, where the Buriganga River’s murky waters lap against crumbling ghats and the air hums with the chaos of rickshaws and street vendors, legends of fear are born and die in whispers. One such legend was Abul Hasnat Kamal, better known as “Galkata Kamal” — Cheek-Cutter Kamal — a name that evoked terror in the 1980s and 1990s. His story, often buried under the glitz of modern Bangladesh’s economic boom, is a gritty tale of transformation: from a humble village boy with a harmonium in hand to the unchallenged don of Dhaka’s criminal underbelly. This is the untold chronicle of a man who ruled through sheer audacity, leaving a trail of blood that stained the city’s soul, until the noose of justice — or perhaps political expediency — claimed him in 2005.</p><p>The Humble Beginnings: From Village Melodies to Urban Mayhem</p><p>Born in a remote village in Bangladesh, Abul Hasnat Kamal arrived in Dhaka in 1974 as a wide-eyed college student, chasing dreams amid the post-independence fervor. The young Kamal was no thug at first; he was a musician, skilled with the harmonium, teaching music and singing to make ends meet. Dhaka in the 1970s was a city in flux — rebuilding after the Liberation War, but riddled with poverty, political instability, and emerging criminal networks. It was here, in the crowded alleys of Old Dhaka, that Kamal’s path veered into darkness.</p><p>The nickname “Galkata” originated from a brutal street brawl. During a fight, an opponent slashed Kamal’s cheek with a broken bottle, leaving a jagged scar that became his signature. But Kamal flipped the script: the scar didn’t mark him as a victim; it branded him as unbreakable. He embraced the moniker, turning a wound into a weapon of intimidation. By the early 1980s, Kamal had shed his musical aspirations for a life of crime, rising rapidly through the ranks of Dhaka’s underworld. He operated solo at first, fearless and unyielding, zipping through the city on motorcycles or jeeps, two pistols brazenly holstered at his waist. Despite being on the government’s “red list” — a designation for high-threat criminals — he moved with impunity, as if the law was just another spectator in his one-man show.</p><p>What propelled this swift ascent? Dhaka’s criminal ecosystem was a toxic brew of poverty, corruption, and political patronage. Gangs controlled everything from extortion rackets to land grabs, often with tacit support from politicians who needed muscle for elections or to settle scores. Kamal, with his village grit and unbridled ambition, fit right in. He wasn’t just a gangster; he was a force of nature, operating without a large crew, relying on his reputation alone to command respect — and fear.</p><p>The Reign of Terror: Blood on the Streets of Dhaka</p><p>By the mid-1980s, Galkata Kamal had become synonymous with Dhaka’s dark side. His crimes were as varied as they were vicious. He was accused of orchestrating numerous murders, often in broad daylight, using firearms for quick kills or sharp blades for more personal, gruesome executions — decapitations that sent shockwaves through the city. Victims ranged from rival gangsters to politicians and businessmen who crossed him. One notorious case involved the killing of a Member of Parliament, a hit that showcased his reach into the corridors of power. Another was the assassination of Juba Dal leader Jafr, a political rival whose death escalated tensions in Dhaka’s volatile political scene.</p><p>Kamal’s vendettas were legendary. He once harbored a grudge against two student leaders from Sohrawardy College who had clashed with him. For months, he fired four rounds daily into their homes, undeterred by police patrols or armed guards. No one dared retaliate; to challenge Kamal was to invite certain death. He broke the unwritten code of the underworld — “murder in revenge for murder” — through sheer bravado. Hired hits were his bread and butter; he killed for money, for loyalty, or simply to assert dominance. Businessmen like Abdul Khaleq Rana and Firoz Al Mamun of Demra fell to his wrath in a double murder that would later seal his fate.</p><p>But Kamal wasn’t without allies. He associated with other top criminals, like Shahidur Rahman, a notorious figure from Old Dhaka who fled to Kolkata in the early 1980s after a death sentence. Shahidur, Kamal’s close associate, lived freely in India for over two decades before his arrest, highlighting the cross-border networks that sustained Bangladesh’s gangsters.</p><p>These connections extended to Kolkata, where many Dhaka criminals sought refuge during crackdowns, blending into the city’s underbelly while plotting their return.</p><p>Kamal’s operations made Dhaka tremble. He controlled extortion rackets, demanding “protection” money from shopkeepers, builders, and even politicians. His “red card” status from the government only amplified his aura; it meant he was untouchable, perhaps protected by higher-ups who benefited from his services. In a city where law enforcement was often corrupt or overwhelmed, Kamal thrived as “Dhaka’s Don,” a self-made emperor in a kingdom of shadows. Stories of his exploits spread like wildfire: the man who could walk into a police station armed and walk out unscathed, the gangster who turned a scar into a symbol of invincibility.</p><p>Yet, beneath the terror, there was a complex figure. Some locals viewed him as a Robin Hood-esque protector, doling out justice in a system that failed the poor. But this romanticization masked the reality: Kamal’s rule was built on violence, and his victims were often innocents caught in the crossfire. Dhaka’s streets ran red with the blood of those who opposed him, and his reign contributed to the city’s reputation as a hotbed of organized crime, alongside figures like Kala Jahangir and Killer Abbas.</p><p>The Political Nexus: Patronage and the Frankenstein Monster</p><p>No gangster rises without patrons, and Kamal’s story is intertwined with Bangladesh’s turbulent politics. The 1980s and 1990s saw gangs like his being used as tools by political parties — Awami League, BNP, and others — to intimidate opponents, rig votes, and control territories. Kamal’s “government patronage” is a key untold aspect: whispers suggest he was shielded by influential figures who saw him as an asset. This protection allowed him to operate openly, but it also sowed the seeds of his downfall.</p><p>In Bangladesh’s underworld, gangsters often doubled as political enforcers. Kamal’s hits on political figures, like the MP and Juba Dal leader, hint at deeper ties. As one source notes, criminals like him fled to India during drives against top-listed offenders, only to return when the heat died down.</p><p>This cycle of patronage and betrayal turned Kamal into a “Frankenstein monster” — created and enabled by the system, only to become too dangerous to control.</p><p>The turning point came in the early 2000s, amid growing public outcry against gang violence. Dhaka’s mastans (gangsters) were in decline, thanks to operations like those targeting figures like Picchi Hannan in Karwan Bazar. Kamal, however, clung to power until his arrest.</p><p>The Fall: Trial, Execution, and a Mother’s Unheard Words</p><p>Kamal’s empire crumbled with his arrest for the 2000 murders of businessmen Rana and Mamun. The trial was swift and damning: in 2005, a Dhaka court sentenced him to death, along with two accomplices (though only Kamal was executed; the others remain at large). On February 4, 2005, he was hanged in Dhaka Central Jail. His final moments were poignant: he reportedly wanted to speak last words to his mother but couldn’t, a humanizing detail in a life defined by brutality.</p><p>The execution marked the end of an era. Kamal’s death was part of a broader crackdown on Dhaka’s gangsters, many of whom fled, died, or faded into obscurity. Yet, his legacy lingers in the city’s collective memory — a reminder of how unchecked ambition and systemic corruption can birth monsters.</p><p>Legacy in Modern Dhaka: Lessons from the Shadows</p><p>Today, Dhaka is a megacity of skyscrapers and startups, but the scars of its underworld persist. Gangs have evolved, with new dons like Bikash Kumar Biswas and Kala Jahangir filling the void, but the old-school terror of Galkata Kamal feels like a relic.</p><p>His story, popularized in YouTube documentaries and whispered tales, serves as a cautionary narrative: of how a talented youth can descend into villainy, and how societies pay the price for ignoring the rot within.</p><p>In retelling Galkata Kamal’s untold story, we confront the uncomfortable truth that heroes and villains are often products of their environment. Dhaka has moved on, but the echoes of his gunfire remind us that the line between melody and mayhem is perilously thin.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=1f26a38bc3b9" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From Cricketer to Crime Don: The Untold Story of Mominullah David]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/from-cricketer-to-crime-don-the-untold-story-of-mominullah-david-10a9871cd111?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/10a9871cd111</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[cricket]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[underworld]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[true-crime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[bangladesh]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[crime]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Mon, 29 Dec 2025 17:49:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2025-12-29T17:49:38.176Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the bustling industrial hub of Narayanganj, Bangladesh, where the Shitalakshya River weaves through a maze of factories, markets, and shadowy alleys, a young man’s dream of cricket glory morphed into a nightmare of violence and power. Mominullah David — once a promising batsman idolizing Australian legend David Boon — rose from the cricket pitches to become one of the most notorious underworld figures in the region’s history. His life, cut short in a hail of bullets during a controversial “crossfire” encounter, embodies the toxic intersection of politics, crime, and survival in Bangladesh’s turbulent 1990s and early 2000s. This modern retelling dives deep into David’s transformation, drawing on archival reports, eyewitness accounts, and recent documentaries to unravel a story that’s equal parts tragedy, ambition, and brutality. It’s a tale that echoes the gritty true-crime narratives of today, like those in podcasts such as Serial or Netflix’s Narcos, but rooted in the chaotic underbelly of South Asian politics.</p><p>The Boy with a Bat: Early Life and Cricket Dreams</p><p>Born in the mid-1960s (exact date unknown) in Narayanganj, a district just outside Dhaka known for its garment factories and river ports, Mominullah Liton — later known as Mominullah David — grew up in a working-class family. His father was a local figure, though details are sparse; what stands out is young Mominullah’s passion for cricket, a sport that captivated Bangladesh long before the country gained Test status in 2000. Inspired by David Boon, the burly Australian batsman famous for his mustache and gritty performances in the 1980s, Mominullah adopted “David” as his alias. Boon, with his no-nonsense style and ability to anchor innings under pressure, became a symbol for the young Bangladeshi, who dreamed of wielding a bat on international stages rather than knives in street brawls.</p><p>David enrolled in the Narayanganj Cricket Academy, where he showed promise as a batsman. Locals recall him as a talented player with a solid technique, often practicing for hours on makeshift pitches. “He batted well,” notes a recent tribute, painting him as a hopeful youth chasing glory in a sport that offered escape from poverty.</p><p>In an era when cricket was exploding in popularity across the subcontinent — thanks to stars like Kapil Dev and Imran Khan — David’s aspirations weren’t far-fetched. He was fondly called “David” after his idol, a nickname that stuck even as his life veered off course. But Narayanganj wasn’t Lord’s or Eden Gardens; it was a hotbed of gang violence, political turf wars, and economic desperation. The 1980s, under the military dictatorship of Hussain Muhammad Ershad, saw rampant corruption and street-level thuggery, setting the stage for David’s pivot from sports to survival.</p><p>The Bloody Baptism: Entry into the Underworld</p><p>David’s descent into crime began on July 24, 1988, amid the chaotic final years of Ershad’s regime. Narayanganj was plagued by territorial disputes between rival groups, often fueled by political patrons who used thugs as enforcers. In a infamous clash between locals from Mishonpara (David’s area) and Chasara, David led a violent attack that left two men — Kamal Ahmed and Abul Kalam — dead. This incident, rooted in a bid for local supremacy, marked his emergence as a criminal force. At just around 20 years old, David was thrust into the spotlight not as a cricketer, but as a killer.</p><p>The murders were no isolated act. Bangladesh’s political landscape in the late 1980s was a breeding ground for such violence, with parties like Ershad’s Jatiya Party (JP) recruiting muscle to maintain control. David aligned himself with JP lawmaker Nasim Osman, a powerful figure who commanded a gang of criminals. Under Osman’s patronage, David honed his skills in extortion and intimidation, collecting “tolls” from transport workers, businessmen, and jhut traders (dealers in garment by-products, a lucrative trade in Narayanganj’s textile boom). This period saw David transform from a local thug into a calculating operator, using violence as currency in a system where law enforcement was often complicit or overwhelmed.</p><p>As democracy returned in 1990 with the fall of Ershad and the rise of the Bangladesh Nationalist Party (BNP) under Khaleda Zia, David switched allegiances seamlessly. He joined the BNP, intensifying his activities and positioning himself against rivals like Shamim Osman, Nasim’s brother and an Awami League (AL) leader. This political flip-flopping was typical in Bangladesh, where criminals thrived by attaching themselves to whichever party held power. David’s cricket dreams faded entirely, replaced by the adrenaline of gang warfare and the allure of quick wealth.</p><p>Building an Empire: Rise to Power and Reign of Terror</p><p>By the mid-1990s, David had ascended to the status of an underworld don, controlling half of Narayanganj’s criminal landscape.</p><p>His operations were sophisticated: extortion rackets targeted bus terminals, hospitals, and garment factories, while kidnappings of wealthy traders brought in ransoms. He amassed a fortune, turning from a modest cricketer-wannabe into a millionaire with luxury vehicles and armed entourages. His three brothers — Tapan, Jewel, and Roman — served as lieutenants, enforcing toll collections with ruthless efficiency. Those who resisted faced dire consequences; David was accused in 31 criminal cases, including seven murders, making him fifth on the police’s most-wanted list in Narayanganj.</p><p>David’s empire wasn’t built on brute force alone. He cultivated a Robin Hood-like image among some locals, protecting BNP supporters and clashing with rival gangs. During the 1990s non-cooperation movement against the government, he led “pier leadership” for the BNP, organizing street protests and countering opposition violence.</p><p>In BNP circles, he was seen as a “fearless soldier” of party founder Ziaur Rahman, a youth leader who rebuilt the party’s presence in Narayanganj by driving out thugs from opposing factions. However, to his victims, he was a terror: stories abound of abductions, beatings, and executions for non-payment.</p><p>When the Awami League came to power in 1996 under Sheikh Hasina, David’s fortunes flipped. He went underground, evading arrest 12 times across the country. His father died during this period, and AL cadres declared him and his brothers “unwanted” in North Narayanganj, seizing control of his territories. But resilience defined David; with the BNP-led alliance’s return in 2001, he resurfaced, backed by a minister and a BNP lawmaker. He unleashed a wave of retribution, expelling Shamim Osman from the area and reclaiming his empire. Under this protection, David became “untouchable,” operating with impunity in a city where politics and crime were indistinguishable.</p><p>The Political Player: Jubo Dal and BNP Ties</p><p>David’s story is inseparable from Bangladesh’s polarized politics. As joint convenor of the Narayanganj City Jubo Dal — the youth wing of the BNP — he wielded influence beyond mere crime. Jubo Dal was notorious for its street-level activism, often veering into violence during elections and protests. David embodied this: a “brave youth group leader” who struck fear into opponents and idolized within his party.</p><p>His role in resisting AL dominance made him a BNP asset, but it also painted a target on his back.</p><p>In the broader context of Bangladesh’s “godfather” culture — where politicians nurture criminal networks for electoral muscle — David was a prime example. He clashed with the Osman family, a dynasty with ties to both major parties, in a feud that mirrored the country’s AL-BNP rivalry. His political backing allowed him to evade justice for years, even securing bail in a murder case months before his death. Yet, this alliance proved double-edged; as the BNP government launched “Operation Clean Heart” in 2002 to curb crime (ironically, amid accusations of targeting opponents), figures like David became liabilities.</p><p>The Fatal Crossfire: Death and Controversy</p><p>On November 24, 2004, David’s reign ended in a dramatic showdown in Dhaka’s Malibagh area. Driving a luxury jeep (Dhaka Metro Gha-11–1691), he was tailed by the Rapid Action Battalion (RAB), an elite anti-crime force formed that year. RAB, notorious for extrajudicial killings labeled as “crossfires,” had planned his arrest since November 11. Near the Malibagh Community Centre, RAB blocked his path. David attempted a U-turn, then fled on foot, firing three shots from a German-made pistol. RAB responded with two bullets to his chest and abdomen, killing him instantly.</p><p>The scene was chaotic: witnesses saw a man and woman escape from his jeep into nearby shanties. RAB seized his weapon and seven bullets, cordoning off the area until late night. His body, adorned with a thick gold chain, was taken to Dhaka Medical College Hospital, where death was confirmed.</p><p>Officially, it was self-defense; critics called it an execution, part of RAB’s pattern of eliminating high-profile criminals — often with political undertones. David’s death, while his party was in power, sparked outrage within BNP ranks, with some labeling it “suicidal politics.” No one from the party attended his funeral, fearing backlash.</p><p>Legacy: Hero or Villain?</p><p>Two decades later, David’s story endures as a cautionary tale. In Narayanganj, some remember him as a protector who ended thug rule and defended the poor against exploiters. Tributes on his “martyrdom” anniversary portray him as a BNP martyr, a “great defense” against oppression. Recent documentaries highlight his loyalty and respect among locals, framing him as a complex anti-hero in Bangladesh’s crime lore.</p><p>Yet, to law enforcement and victims’ families, he was a monster responsible for untold suffering. His death brought relief to many in the industrial district, where his extortion crippled businesses. In today’s Bangladesh, amid ongoing debates over RAB’s tactics and political violence, David’s life underscores how ambition, when twisted by systemic failures, breeds dons from dreamers.</p><p>Mominullah David’s untold story isn’t just about one man — it’s a mirror to a nation’s struggles with corruption, power, and redemption. From the crack of a cricket bat to the echo of gunshots, his path reminds us that heroes and villains often share the same origin story.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=10a9871cd111" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Butcher of Delhi: Chandrakant Jha’s Reign of Terror in the Shadows of the City]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/the-butcher-of-delhi-chandrakant-jhas-reign-of-terror-in-the-shadows-of-the-city-a4f5d8d69b0c?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/a4f5d8d69b0c</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[crime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[india]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[serial-killers]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[true-crime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[murder]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sun, 28 Dec 2025 15:59:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2025-12-28T15:59:37.172Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the bustling chaos of Delhi’s underbelly, where migrants chase dreams amid grinding poverty, a monster lurked in plain sight. Chandrakant Jha, a seemingly ordinary hawker from Bihar, transformed into one of India’s most notorious serial killers, earning the moniker “The Butcher of Delhi.” From 1998 to 2007, he allegedly slaughtered up to 18 young men, dismembering their bodies with chilling precision and scattering the parts like macabre puzzles across the city. His crimes weren’t just murders — they were statements, taunts scrawled on bloodstained notes challenging the police to catch him. Today, in a world obsessed with true crime podcasts and Netflix docs, Jha’s story feels eerily modern: a tale of immigrant rage, psychological trauma, and a broken system that let him slip through the cracks multiple times. But beneath the gore lies a deeper narrative about class, migration, and the dark side of urban India.</p><p>From Rural Bihar to Delhi’s Gritty Streets: Jha’s Early Life</p><p>Born in 1967 in the sleepy village of Ghosai in Bihar’s Madhepura district , Chandrakant Jha’s childhood was marred by neglect and dysfunction. His mother, a schoolteacher, was often absent or uncaring, fueling village gossip about her “imbalance” This maternal abandonment planted seeds of deep-seated resentment, which forensic psychologists later linked to his crimes — a hatred for the “mother figure” that he projected onto his victims. Jha’s father isn’t mentioned much in records, but the overall family dynamic left him isolated, fostering an urge for control that would define his adult life.</p><p>Like millions of others, Jha migrated to Delhi in search of better opportunities. He settled in the crowded Azadpur Mandi, one of Asia’s largest wholesale vegetable markets, where he hawked produce. Life was tough: low wages, relentless hustle, and constant police harassment. Jha claimed cops demanded bribes, igniting a burning grudge against authority. He married twice — abandoning his first wife after a year and fathering five daughters with his second, though he lived mostly apart from them in Haiderpur, a migrant-heavy neighborhood in West Delhi. To outsiders, he was just another struggling Bihari immigrant. But inside, something simmered.</p><p>The First Kill: A Spark Ignites the Butcher</p><p>Jha’s descent into murder began in 1998 with a petty altercation. A fellow dealer named Pandit (also known as Mangal) crossed him — perhaps over money or a dispute at the mandi. Enraged, Jha attacked, injuring Pandit severely. But it escalated: He strangled him, then hacked off his head, limbs, and hands with surgical-like efficiency, minimizing blood spillage in what he later called an “elegant” operation. Pandit’s head was never found, dumped presumably in the Yamuna River. Police arrested Jha that year, but he was released in 2002 due to insufficient evidence. Free again, he didn’t stop — he evolved.</p><p>This first kill set the pattern. Jha targeted vulnerable young men, often fellow migrants from Bihar or Uttar Pradesh, aged 18–30. He’d befriend them, offer jobs as hawkers in weekly bazaars, share meals, and treat them like brothers. But minor infractions — lying, stealing, eating non-vegetarian food, smoking ganja, or “womanizing” — triggered his rage. He’d tie their hands as “punishment,” strangle them with a homemade nanchaku (wooden stakes linked by a chain), and dismember the bodies. Sometimes, he’d remove the penis or other parts, adding a layer of humiliation. He even photographed victims bound and helpless, souvenirs of his dominance.</p><p>The Killing Spree: Bodies in Baskets and Rivers</p><p>Post-release, Jha’s murders accelerated. In 2003, he killed Shekhar and Umesh, both young migrants he’d housed and employed. Guddu followed in 2005, Anil Mandal in 2006, and then Upender and Dilip in 2007. Authorities allege up to 18 victims total, though he was only charged in seven cases. The disposals were theatrical: Bodies packed in plastic bags or baskets, transported via a modified cycle-rickshaw with a scooter engine, and dumped in public spots. Heads often ended up in the polluted Yamuna, while torsos appeared outside Tihar Jail — Delhi’s massive prison complex — symbolizing his contempt for the system.</p><p>One infamous discovery in October 2006: A decapitated body wrapped in newspaper and rags inside a basket at Tihar’s Gate №3, with a note spewing abuse and daring the police. A year later, another mutilated corpse surfaced, limbs and genitals severed. Then, just a month after, a third. No fingerprints, no IDs — India lacked a national DNA database, making identification a nightmare. Jha’s notes, signed “Tumhara baap + Jijaji. CC” (Your father + brother-in-law. CC), promised more killings if he wasn’t caught. He’d even call police to tip off body locations, turning murder into a twisted game.</p><p>Taunting the Titans: Jha’s War on the Police</p><p>What set Jha apart wasn’t just the brutality — it was the bravado. His letters were laced with maternal insults, echoing his own trauma. He craved fame, frustrated by the lack of media spotlight on his crimes. In a city of 20 million, his acts were a bid for power amid powerlessness. As a low-wage immigrant, Jha embodied the stresses of urban migration: exploitation, alienation, and toxic masculinity. Experts see his killings as a “power play,” where dominating victims compensated for his own emasculation.</p><p>Police struggled. Initial leads fizzled; bodies were too mutilated. But in 2007, sub-inspector Narendra Pehalwan recalled the 1998 case. Using informants in migrant communities, they tracked Jha to Haiderpur. Arrested in May 2007 (though some reports say January), he confessed on one condition: no beatings. In interrogations, he detailed his methods, blaming his parents and police corruption. A special team, led by Additional Commissioner Sanjay Sain, pieced together the puzzle after Jha jumped parole earlier.</p><p>The Trial: From Death Row to Life in the Shadows</p><p>Jha’s trial was a media circus. In February 2013, he was convicted on three murder counts: death sentences for two, life for the third. But in January 2016, the Delhi High Court commuted the deaths to life without remission. Now 58, he’s back in Tihar — the very jail he mocked — serving his sentence. Parole has been a rollercoaster: Revoked in 2020, denied in 2022, but granted 90 days in August 2023 for his eldest daughter’s wedding arrangements. At 60 (as of recent reports), he’s unlikely to taste freedom again.</p><p>Unpacking the Psyche: What Made the Butcher Tick?</p><p>Clinical forensics expert S.L. Vaya analyzed Jha’s letters, pinpointing his maternal disdain as a core driver. His vague excuses for killing — petty habits — masked a deeper need for control. In a patriarchal society, Jha’s acts screamed fragile masculinity: Tying up victims, photographing them, mutilating genitals. Netflix’s Indian Predator: The Butcher of Delhi (released July 20, 2022) dives into this, produced by VICE Studios. Director Ayesha Sood and researcher Nandita Gupta visited his Bihar village, uncovering victim photos that still haunt locals. The series frames Jha as a product of systemic failures: Poverty, migration stress, and inadequate policing.</p><p>Legacy: A Cautionary Tale in Modern India</p><p>Jha’s story resonates in today’s India, where serial killers like him exploit urban anonymity. It highlights biases against migrants — often labeled “Bihari” with disdain — and the need for better forensics, like a national DNA registry. True crime fans devour his tale on podcasts (like Two Crime Besties) and docs, but for victims’ families, it’s unending grief. Delhi has moved on, but the Butcher’s shadow lingers, a reminder that monsters don’t always hide — they blend in, waiting for the next slight to strike.</p><p>In an era of social media vigilantism and instant notoriety, Jha’s taunts feel prescient. He wanted fame; now, he’s immortalized in pixels. But at what cost? As one investigator put it, his crimes were “a cry for attention in a city that ignores the invisible.” Delhi’s Butcher may be caged, but his story warns us: Ignore the marginalized, and the darkness festers.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=a4f5d8d69b0c" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Day the Women of Kasturba Nagar Fought Back: Inside the 2004 Lynching of Akku Yadav]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/the-day-the-women-of-kasturba-nagar-fought-back-inside-the-2004-lynching-of-akku-yadav-c5ea128fe267?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/c5ea128fe267</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[crime]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[rape]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[india]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[womens-rights]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[true-crime]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2025 14:50:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2025-12-27T14:50:30.782Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the sweltering heat of a Nagpur courtroom on August 13, 2004, a scene unfolded that would shock India and spark global conversations about justice, gender violence, and the failures of the system. Bharat Kalicharan Yadav, better known as Akku Yadav — a notorious gangster who had terrorized a slum community for over a decade — was lynched in broad daylight by a mob of hundreds of women. Armed with vegetable knives, stones, and chili powder, they stabbed him over 70 times, hacked off his penis, and left his body in a pool of blood on the courtroom floor. This wasn’t just an act of vengeance; it was a desperate cry from a community abandoned by the very institutions meant to protect them.</p><p>Two decades later, as movements like #MeToo and discussions around vigilante justice continue to dominate headlines, the story of Akku Yadav’s death remains a chilling reminder of what happens when the oppressed take the law into their own hands.</p><p>This modern retelling draws from eyewitness accounts, court documents, and investigative reports to unpack the events leading up to that fateful day, the lynching itself, and its ripple effects. It’s a tale of systemic rot, caste-based oppression, and female solidarity that feels eerily relevant in today’s world of unchecked power and delayed justice.</p><p>From Milkman’s Son to Slum Tyrant: The Rise of Akku Yadav</p><p>Born in 1971 or 1972 in the heart of Kasturba Nagar, a sprawling slum in Nagpur, Maharashtra, Akku Yadav grew up in a world of poverty and petty crime.</p><p>The son of a milkman, he had two brothers, Santosh and Yuvraj, and quickly immersed himself in the rival gangs that dominated the area. By his early 20s, Yadav had transformed from a local nuisance into a full-blown criminal overlord, building a small empire through extortion, robbery, and violence.</p><p>His gang controlled the slum’s 300 families, many of whom were Dalits — India’s historically marginalized “untouchable” caste — making them easy targets for exploitation.</p><p>Yadav’s criminal career kicked off in 1991 with a gang rape, setting the tone for a reign of terror that would last until 2004.</p><p>Over the years, he was linked to at least three murders, where victims’ bodies were dumped on nearby railroad tracks to simulate accidents. But it was his systematic use of sexual violence as a tool of control that made him infamous. Reports suggest he raped over 40 women and girls, with the youngest victim just 10 years old.</p><p>In nearly every other house in Kasturba Nagar, there was a rape survivor. He targeted Dalit women specifically, knowing societal stigma and caste biases would silence them.</p><p>His methods were brutal and calculated. Yadav and his gang would barge into homes, demanding money or goods from shops without payment. If resisted, they resorted to torture, assault, or worse. One chilling incident involved stripping a man naked and burning him with cigarettes in front of his daughter.</p><p>In another, he gang-raped a woman just days after her wedding, and publicly assaulted a pregnant woman. A new mother who was raped by his gang later died by suicide after setting herself on fire with kerosene. Girls as young as 12 were dragged to derelict buildings for repeated assaults.</p><p>Yadav’s impunity stemmed from his cozy relationship with the local police. Arrested 14 times, he was detained for a year in 1999 under Maharashtra’s preventive detention laws and even banned from Nagpur in January 2004. Yet, he always walked free, thanks to bribes of cash and alcohol. Police not only tipped him off about complaints but sometimes participated in the abuse — one victim was gang-raped by officers after reporting Yadav. When women reported rapes, they were dismissed as “loose” or accused of affairs.</p><p>A Community in Chains: The Human Cost of Terror</p><p>Life in Kasturba Nagar under Yadav’s shadow was a nightmare. Families lived in constant fear: children stopped attending school, women avoided leaving home, and no one dared host celebrations or accept marriage proposals. Many fled the slum altogether, while others pulled girls out of education to protect them. Daily-wage laborers and domestic workers, mostly Dalits, were extorted relentlessly — Yadav’s gang looted bikes, phones, and even homes.</p><p>Personal stories paint a harrowing picture. Resha Raut, whose sister Asha Bhagat ran a small alcohol business, recalled how Asha confronted Yadav about his extortion and rapes. In 1999, Yadav slit Asha’s throat, cut off her ears and breasts, and stole her jewelry — all in front of her 14-year-old daughter, Megha. He later turned her home into a gang hangout. Megha, traumatized, couldn’t testify, leading to Yadav’s light sentence. Resha’s mother, Anjanabai Borkar, endured threats like “If you don’t give me money today, I will strip you naked.”</p><p>The justice system’s failures amplified the despair. Cases like the 1991 gang rape dragged on for years, with courts granting bail repeatedly under a “bail not jail” mindset, ignoring Yadav’s history. A survey post-lynching showed 73% of locals had lost faith in the system, viewing it as biased toward the powerful.</p><p>The Spark: Usha Narayane’s Defiant Stand</p><p>The turning point came in early August 2004. Usha Narayane, a 25-year-old call-center worker and Dalit activist, helped a rape victim file a complaint against Yadav. Enraged, Yadav and 40 men surrounded her home, threatening acid attacks and rape. Narayane dragged a gas cylinder to the door, opened the valve, and threatened to blow them up, forcing a retreat.</p><p>Emboldened, she rallied the slum door-to-door: “The water has spilled over the edge. We have to unite.” Residents armed themselves, attacked Yadav’s associates, and on August 6, burned his house down. Fearing for his life, Yadav “surrendered” to police on August 7 for protection. A mob tried to attack him during a court appearance on August 8, but he survived.</p><p>Blood on the Courtroom Floor: The Lynching</p><p>On August 13, 2004, between 2:30 and 3:00 PM, 200 to 400 women (and some men) from Kasturba Nagar marched to Nagpur District Courtroom №7 for Yadav’s bail hearing. They sat near the front, concealed weapons at the ready. Yadav arrived cocky, escorted by just three unarmed constables despite prior threats.</p><p>Spotting a victim, he sneered, calling her a prostitute and vowing to rape her again. She struck him with her sandal, yelling, “We can’t both live on this Earth together. It’s you or me.” Chaos erupted. The mob surged, stabbing him 70–73 times — each woman taking a turn — throwing chili powder in his eyes and at fleeing police, and one severing his penis. Yadav begged for mercy: “Forgive me! I won’t do it again!” But within 15 minutes, he was dead, his blood splattered on walls and floors.</p><p>Police claimed four men did the killing, with women shielding them, but survivors insisted it was a collective act of women-led retribution. The autopsy revealed alcohol in his system, hinting at preferential treatment in custody.</p><p>Aftermath: Celebrations, Arrests, and Acquittals</p><p>Back in the slum, women celebrated with music, dancing, food, and fruit distribution — a rare moment of joy. But repercussions followed. Five women, including Narayane and Borkar, were arrested for murder. Protests erupted: 400 women, men, and children stormed the court, chanting “Arrest us all!” and refusing to leave until bail was granted. They were released after demonstrations, with Narayane facing additional “anti-nationalist” charges seen as retaliation for exposing police failures.</p><p>By 2012–2014, all 21 accused (including 14 men and seven women) were acquitted due to lack of evidence, unreliable witnesses, and police bias. Retired judge Bhau Vahane praised the women: “They had no alternative.” Public support was overwhelming — 81% approved the motive in surveys.</p><p>Why It Happened: Systemic Failures and Vigilante Justice</p><p>The lynching wasn’t premeditated murder; it was the boiling point of years of neglect. Police complicity, judicial delays, and caste discrimination left residents with no recourse. Nagpur had a history of vigilantism, with prior lynchings highlighting governance gaps.</p><p>Human rights reports criticized the criminal justice system for not using laws like the Maharashtra Control of Organised Crime Act against Yadav and failing to protect witnesses. Recommendations included better enforcement of externment orders, judicious bail decisions, and accessible justice for the poor.</p><p>Echoes in the Modern Era</p><p>Today, the Akku Yadav case resonates in an age of social media activism and true-crime obsessions. It’s been depicted in documentaries like Candles in the Wind (2011), films such as 200: Halla Ho (2021), and Netflix’s Indian Predator: Murder in a Courtroom (2022), which features victim interviews. It parallels global stories of women rising against predators, from the Delhi bus rape protests to #MeToo revelations.</p><p>Yet, it raises tough questions: Is vigilante justice ever justified? In a system rigged against the marginalized, what choices remain? As Anjanabai Borkar reflected, “He used to tell me, ‘If you don’t give me money today, I will strip you naked.’ I have a lot of pain… What do I do alone?” The women of Kasturba Nagar answered with blood, forcing India to confront its shadows. Two decades on, the debate rages: heroines or criminals? Perhaps both, in a world that failed them first.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=c5ea128fe267" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mystery Beneath the Ice: The Lost Submarine Ran and Antarctica’s Hidden Melting World]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@iram.ahmed1997/mystery-beneath-the-ice-the-lost-submarine-ran-and-antarcticas-hidden-melting-world-48b41d064e4c?source=rss-a83c7f0caac5------2</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://medium.com/p/48b41d064e4c</guid>
            <category><![CDATA[world]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[submarine]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[mystery]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[lost]]></category>
            <category><![CDATA[antarctica]]></category>
            <dc:creator><![CDATA[Iram Ahmed]]></dc:creator>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Dec 2025 17:46:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <atom:updated>2025-12-26T17:46:43.501Z</atom:updated>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the frozen expanse of Antarctica, where temperatures plummet to bone-chilling lows and ice shelves stretch like colossal barriers against the encroaching sea, a robotic explorer named Ran ventured into the unknown. This autonomous underwater vehicle (AUV), a sleek, yellow submarine about the size of a small car, was designed to slip beneath the Dotson Ice Shelf in West Antarctica — a floating slab of ice roughly the size of Connecticut. Its mission: to map the hidden underside of the ice, revealing how warm ocean currents are gnawing away at this critical structure from below. What Ran discovered was a landscape of bizarre, anomalous formations: teardrop-shaped craters, terraced steps, and swirling channels that looked like they could have been sculpted by an otherworldly force. But then, after transmitting its groundbreaking data, Ran vanished without a trace, its signal lost in the icy abyss.</p><p>This story isn’t the stuff of science fiction or conspiracy theories — though the headlines might suggest otherwise. It’s a tale rooted in cutting-edge oceanography and the urgent realities of climate change. In 2022, during a research expedition aboard the South Korean icebreaker RV Araon, scientists from the University of Gothenburg in Sweden deployed Ran to probe the Dotson Ice Shelf. The findings, published in the journal Science Advances in late 2024, have reshaped our understanding of how Antarctica’s ice is responding to a warming world. And the submarine’s disappearance adds a poignant layer of drama to an already high-stakes scientific endeavor. As we face escalating sea-level rise and more frequent extreme weather events in 2025, stories like this underscore the fragility of our planet’s polar regions.</p><p>The Mission: Venturing into the Dark</p><p>Antarctica’s ice shelves are the floating extensions of massive glaciers that flow from the continent’s interior. They act like buttresses, holding back the land-based ice and slowing its slide into the ocean. If these shelves thin or collapse, the glaciers behind them accelerate, dumping more ice into the sea and contributing to global sea-level rise. The Dotson Ice Shelf, part of the Amundsen Sea sector in West Antarctica, is particularly vulnerable. It’s pinned above a deep ocean basin where warm, salty water from the Circumpolar Deep Water (CDW) current can infiltrate and erode the ice from beneath — a process known as basal melting.</p><p>Enter Ran, named after the Norse goddess of the drowned. This state-of-the-art AUV, developed by Kongsberg Maritime and operated by the University of Gothenburg, is equipped with multibeam sonar, acoustic Doppler current profilers, and other sensors to create high-resolution 3D maps of underwater environments. Unlike crewed submarines, Ran operates autonomously, navigating pre-programmed paths without real-time human input. This makes it ideal for risky under-ice missions where GPS signals can’t penetrate and radio communication is impossible.</p><p>The 2022 expedition, part of the International Thwaites Glacier Collaboration (ITGC), aimed to explain a puzzling asymmetry in Dotson’s melting patterns. Satellite data showed the eastern side of the shelf melting slowly, remaining thick and stable, while the western side was thinning rapidly — losing ice at rates up to 40 feet per year in some spots. “We needed to see what’s happening down there, where the action is,” explained Anna Wåhlin, a professor of oceanographic physics at the University of Gothenburg and the mission’s lead. “Ran was our eyes in the dark.”</p><p>Over 27 days, Ran completed 14 dives, weaving up to 11 miles into the cavity beneath the 1,150-foot-thick ice shelf. Each mission lasted from several hours to over a day, with the sub surfacing at designated rendezvous points to upload data. The vehicle mapped an area of about 54 square miles — equivalent to a small city — providing the most detailed under-ice imagery ever captured.</p><p>Anomalous Discoveries: A Sculpted Underworld</p><p>What Ran revealed was nothing short of astonishing. The underside of the Dotson Ice Shelf wasn’t the smooth, uniform surface scientists had imagined. Instead, it was a dynamic, sculpted landscape riddled with features that spoke to the relentless power of ocean currents.</p><p>In the eastern and central regions, Ran imaged vast plateaus interrupted by terraced steps, resembling giant staircases etched into the ice. These terraces, stacked like layers of a frozen cake, formed as bursts of slightly warmer water periodically flooded the cavity, stripping away horizontal layers of ice over decades. “It’s like peeling an onion,” Wåhlin noted in interviews following the data analysis. “Each terrace records a past influx of heat.”</p><p>Deeper in, especially on the western side, the ice base transitioned to smoother expanses carved with channels and scooped depressions. Here, fast-moving currents created swirling patterns and teardrop-shaped pits — some as long as 984 feet and as deep as 164 feet. These features, invisible from satellites, were formed by turbulent water flows near the grounding line, where the ice shelf meets the seafloor. The teardrops pointed downstream, indicating the direction of the erosive currents, much like wind-sculpted dunes in a desert.</p><p>Ran also captured evidence of full-thickness fractures slicing through the shelf. These cracks, some dating back to the 1990s, had been widened and smoothed at their bases by melting. Warm water channeled through these fractures acted like highways for heat, concentrating erosion and accelerating ice loss. “Fractures are game-changers,” said co-researcher Karen Heywood from the University of East Anglia. “They steer the warm water right where it does the most damage.”</p><p>The data explained Dotson’s east-west divide: Warm CDW infiltrates primarily from the west, driven by ocean circulation patterns, while colder, fresher water protects the east. In slow-flow areas, melting creates those stepped terraces; in high-shear zones, turbulence smooths and grooves the ice. These insights challenge existing climate models, which often overlook such small-scale features. “Most models treat the ice base as flat,” Wåhlin said. “But Ran shows it’s anything but.”</p><p>The Vanishing: Loss of Signal and a Scientific Setback</p><p>Tragedy struck on what was meant to be an extension of the mapping efforts. After successfully completing its initial dives, Ran was deployed for another under-ice run to gather more data on the western melt zones. Programmed to return to an open-water pickup point after over 24 hours of autonomous operation, the sub simply… didn’t show up.</p><p>Search teams on the RV Araon scoured the area, pinging for acoustic signals and scanning for debris. Nothing. “To see Ran disappear into the dark, unknown depths below the ice, executing her tasks for over 24 hours without communication, is of course daunting,” Wåhlin reflected.</p><p>Possible explanations include a mechanical failure — perhaps a battery issue or sensor malfunction — or a collision with an unseen ice ridge or seafloor obstacle. The harsh environment, with crushing pressures and sub-zero temperatures, leaves little margin for error.</p><p>Ran’s loss is a blow to the research community. Valued at around $3 million, it’s one of only a few AUVs capable of such deep under-ice work. But the data it transmitted before vanishing is invaluable, already informing new models of ice-shelf dynamics. “We’ve lost a tool, but gained knowledge that could help save coastlines,” said one team member in a post-mission briefing.</p><p>Broader Implications: A Warning from the Poles</p><p>The Dotson Ice Shelf’s story is a microcosm of Antarctica’s broader crisis. Since 1979, the continent’s ice loss has contributed about 0.55 inches to global sea levels, with West Antarctica bearing the brunt. Dotson alone added 0.02 inches between 1979 and 2017. As ocean temperatures rise — driven by human-induced climate change — warm currents like CDW are penetrating farther and faster, undermining shelves like Dotson and its neighbor, the massive Thwaites Glacier (often called the “Doomsday Glacier”).</p><p>If Thwaites fully collapses, it could raise sea levels by over two feet, inundating coastal cities from Miami to Mumbai. Ran’s findings highlight how features like terraces and fractures amplify this risk by funneling heat efficiently. “Understanding these processes lets us refine predictions,” Wåhlin emphasized. “We can better forecast how much ice West Antarctica might lose in the coming decades.”</p><p>In 2025, as global leaders convene for the latest UN Climate Summit amid record-breaking heatwaves and floods, Ran’s data serves as a stark reminder. Technologies like AUVs are pushing the boundaries of exploration, but the poles remain perilous frontiers. Plans are underway for a replacement vehicle, dubbed Ran II, with enhanced navigation and redundancy systems. Meanwhile, satellite missions like NASA’s ICESat-2 and ESA’s CryoSat continue monitoring from above, complementing the ground-truth from below.</p><p>Echoes of Exploration: From Shackleton to Modern Mysteries</p><p>Ran’s tale echoes historic Antarctic expeditions, like Ernest Shackleton’s Endurance, lost in 1915 and rediscovered in 2022. But today’s challenges are amplified by climate urgency. Social media buzzed with speculation about Ran’s “anomalous structures” — some users invoking aliens or lost civilizations — but scientists quickly clarified: These are natural formations, sculpted by physics, not phantoms.</p><p>Yet, the mystery of Ran’s disappearance lingers. Was it trapped under shifting ice? Did a rogue current carry it away? As Wåhlin put it, “The ocean keeps its secrets.” In an era of rapid environmental change, unlocking those secrets could be key to our future. The lost submarine may be gone, but its legacy endures — a beacon illuminating the hidden threats beneath the ice.</p><img src="https://medium.com/_/stat?event=post.clientViewed&referrerSource=full_rss&postId=48b41d064e4c" width="1" height="1" alt="">]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>